do you want to grow your glutes without
growing your leg if so this video is for
you in this video I'm going to discuss
why it's so hard to grow the glutes
without growing the legs I'm going to
tell you which exercises you should
avoid if you're trying to grow the
glutes without growing the legs and also
tell you which exercises you should
focus on if trying to grow the glutes
without growing the leg so what's the
deal with the glutes why is it so
complicated well I would argue that
building glutes is not that complicated
but building glutes without building the
legs is complicated so why is this
what's the deal with the glutes well the
glutes are the largest muscle in the
human body they're the Keystone if you
look at a human muscular anatomy chart
you hone in on the glutes they're the
centerpiece they tie a lot of things
together the glut Max has bony
attachments to the pelvis the sacrum the
coxic and the femur so that ties a lot
of important things together you've got
connections through the thoraco lumbar
fascia up through the lat to the humoris
you've got connections to the IT band
down to the tibia you going to have
fascial connections to the pelvic floor
so the glute Max influences a lot of
movement with its main actions being hip
extension hip external rotation and hip
abduction that pretty much sums up the
majority of athletic movements and
through its fasal connections you're
connecting the upper arm to the opposite
lower leg so the glutax is responsible
for numerous important joint actions and
stabilization tasks one would assume
that it would be easy to isolate the
different gluteus maximus subdivision
unfortunately that's wishful thinking
you see the hip is a ball and socket
joint you've got two major ball and
socket joints in the body the hip and
the shoulder think about the shoulder
having the front delts the side delts
the rear delts those do a lot of things
well same with the hip at the hip you've
got hip flexion extension you've got add
uction and abduction you've got internal
and external rotation you also have
anterior and posterior pic tilt you have
abduction in the frontal plane and the
transverse plane and in sports you have
combined actions you know the glutes are
known as a multipler or a tripler
exercise because they create movement in
three different planes the sadal plane
the frontal plane and the transverse
plane and you look at the fiber
directions of the glute Max running down
at around a 45° angle you can see that
it's not just built for hip extension if
it were just built for hip extension
it'd be more like a hamstring more
vertical in nature but because of this
unique fiber Direction you got massive
stabilization at the SI joint you also
have a muscle that's very well designed
for hip external rotation the upper
fibers are better abductors the lower
fibers better hip extensors but it's not
as simple as a hinge joint you know
think of the knee a simple hinge joint
is built for mainly two tests you know
knee extension knee flexion in general
the quads produce knee extension and
mainly the hammies produce knee flexion
these hinge joints are much more simple
than the ball and socket joints and
because these joint actions are so
important it makes sense from an
evolutionary perspective that we don't
just rely on one muscle for hip
extension for example cuz what if that
muscle got injured what if you know a
large animal bit you on the butt and
took out your glutose Maximus you
wouldn't be able to walk so in order to
assist with our survival with our
longevity as a species you've got a lot
of synergist with hip extension you've
got the hamstrings the adductor Magnus
and the glutitis Maximus and it's hard
to isolate the glutes during hip
extension in general you're going to use
all three of them now say you want to
perform hip extension and you want to
Target the glute Max as much as possible
well how do you take the hamstrings out
of it well you can bend the knee and do
bent knee hip extension the bent knee is
going to shorten the hamstring you're
going to slacken it weaken it and then
the glute Max will do a little bit more
how do you take the adductor Magnus out
of it now anytime you go super deep in a
deep hip flexion like a deep squat
you're going to heavily use the adductor
for hip extension because it has really
good leverage at the bottom of a squat
so in theory you either wouldn't go deep
or you'd need to try a different
strategy such as using the Glu dator
where you carry out simultaneous hip
extension and hip abduction
theoretically that would take the
adductors out of it or perhaps wearing a
band around the knees so you're
simultaneously producing hip abduction
and hip extension perhaps that would
reduce adductor recruitment or you could
also focus on exercise like hip thrust
or kickbacks which are not very hard in
the stretch position all right a lot of
the best glute exercises squats love
lunges step UPS single leg leg presses
Bulgarian split squats they're all going
to utilize simultaneous knee and hip
extension you're going to extend both
joints at the same time so you
necessarily have to use the quads and
the hip extensors now because the knee
is so bent during those deep squatting
Tas it will reduce hamstring recruitment
but you're still going to work your
adductors substantially and you're going
to necessarily work the quads and
there's evidence that when you carry out
simultaneous knee and hip extension the
glutes do a little bit less they don't
fire quite as hard as they do when it
just carries out hip extens something
about the nervous system knowing you're
doing two things maybe we should
maximally fire the glutes maybe we
should rely more on the quads we don't
know why this happens but it does indeed
happen the other thing you need to
consider is when you go very deep the
glutes don't activate very well in super
deep hip flexion the glutes are pretty
silent so how do you activate them in
deep hip flexion one strategy is to wear
a band on the knees but that has not
been proven that's just a theory at this
point all right what if you do kneeling
glute exercises like like kneeling
squats kneeling hip thrusts well you're
going to shorten the hamstring take the
hamstrings out of it a little bit you
end up not going quite as deep so you
take the adductors out of it a little
bit but now you're working the glutes
through a shorter range of motion and
you'll still likely feel it in the quads
whenever you do vertical hip extension
exercise you're going to work the glutes
very well in a stretch position now this
is true of rdls good mornings all types
of squats all single leg squat
variations like lunges with the problem
with vertical movements they always work
other muscles with it when you do Ral
and good morning you're going to work
the hamstrings very well when you do
Squat and lunge variations you're going
to work the quads very well so a
solution to that is do more horizontal
hip extension exercises right now we
think that vertical and horizontal hip
extension exercise appear to be roughly
equal at growing the glutes but the nice
thing about horizontal hip extension
exercise they're not as hard on the body
they don't beat you up as much they're
not as hard to recover from so you can
carry them out more frequently or with
greater volume now what about hip
external rotation can you just do that
and Target the glutes well unfortunately
the Deep six external rotators also
carry out hip external rotation so
you're going to work those too and those
muscles are also going to assist in
transverse plain hip abduction so when
you do seated hip abductions you're
going to get help out from the deep six
you're also going to get some help out
from the posterior fibers of the glut
medius and Minimus and maybe some of the
tfl as well so I just mentioned hip
abduction in the transverse plane now
what about the frontal plane the upper
glute Mac seems to work decently as a
frontal plane hip abductor but the glute
medius and Minimus are the primary hip
abductors in the frontal plane yes the
tfl will help out a little bit too so
you can kind of perform Kickbacks at an
angle back but we don't know which angle
would be optimal to involve as much
upper glute Max as possible without
involving the glute medius and Minimus
because again those are the primary hip
abductors in the frontal plane and
finally postor pelvic tilt so even if
there were great postor pelvic tilt
exercises theoretically the rectus
abdominis also produces posterior pelvic
tilt so it's a synergist so you could
theoretically produce posterior pelvic
tilt relying more on the ABS compared to
the glut but in general during hip
extension exercises posterior pelvic
tilt is mostly glute whereas hip flexion
exercises is mostly ABS when you post
your pelvic tilt so I just gave you a
good breakdown of the role of the glutes
and listed off the numerous syes during
gluteus maximus exercises and while we
can theorize about the effectiveness of
the different types of exercise
unfortunately most hypertrophy studies
that we have and we only have a handful
of good glute Max training studies to go
by but almost all of them involve hip
extension we don't have a lot of studies
you know examining hip abduction in the
frontal transverse plane hip external
rotation and posterior pelvic tilt and
looking at how effectively they grow the
glutes I think most experts would agree
that hip extension exercises are going
to be king for glute development they
move you through the most range of
motion and they're definitely the most
popular glute exercises but as I
previously mentioned it's really hard to
Target the glutes during hip extension
and so if you're trying to grow the
glutes without growing the legs it
becomes more important to add in these
other joint actions because if you rely
solely on hip extension you're probably
going to build the legs too and it'll
also be very hard to maximize lower
glute Max size if you didn't perform
vertical hip extension exerts because
theoretically they're the most effective
at hitting the low glutes although the
only study to date the Plotkin 2023
study showed equal lower glute growth
with hip thrust and squats I still kind
of think based on soreness you know when
you do really hard squats or step UPS or
lunges split squats you feel the lower
glutes the next day more so than when
you do hip thrusts or kickbacks or back
extensions so we really need to put a
lot of thought into this so with that in
mind what exercises are definitely out
what exercises should you completely
avoid if you're trying to grow the
glutes without growing the legs first
off would be upright squat variations so
this is your goblet squats your front
squats your high bar squats your deep
squats your hack squats your pendulum
squats your V squats your leg presses
with a low foot position and all of your
single leg movements where your knee
travels far over your toes where you
stay pretty upright all of those are out
why because they're all going to
massively grow the quads and you don't
want quad growth I know you probably
love some of these we all do but you
have to be scientific with your training
so don't do any of those oh what can you
do instead you can do glute dominant
variations of these lifts and I want you
to pay attention to this shape okay this
shape here is what I want to see with
all glute dominant quad exercises so if
you do a squat you're going to do a
vertical Shin parallel box squat you
might not be able to keep The Shins
perfectly vertical but you try to keep
them as vertical as possible and reach
back sit back why are you going to do
that because that's going to reduce the
knee extension moment and increase the
hip extension moment and what that means
is you're going to increase the demands
on the glutes and adductors and decrease
the demands on the knee and the same
shape that same exact shape applies for
leg presses leg presses double leg and
single leg put your foot high on the
platform lunges and split squats I want
you you leaning forward and sitting back
keeping that Shin pretty vertical step
UPS you're going to sit back and lean so
with the single ERS you want a long
stride Big Lean just go to parallel
don't go deeper and a pretty vertical
Shin now these are still going to work
the quads and they're still going to
work the adductors so when you do these
exercises you're only going to do two
sets don't do three sets don't do four
sets and do these sporadically these are
not going to be the Cornerstone of your
program look at all of these movements
they all look pretty similar all right
what else is out standing hinge
exercises so this applies to good
mornings deadlifts and there's single
leg variations too and I know I know I
know you love these exercises but they
work your hamstrings very well and if
you want your glutes to look
proportionally as big as possible you
can't have big hamstrings think about
this if you get bigger legs without
growing your glutes then your glutes
look even smaller they look flatter so
if you're struggling with your glutes
and you want your glutes to appear
bigger you can't grow the hamstrings too
much no good mornings no single egg
variations of these so no single leg
good mornings or single leg stiff leg
deadlifts but what you could do and
again just like with this with the glute
dominant squats you can do glute
dominant standing hinges that's a
Romanian deadlift now in theory you
could do a good morning that looks like
an RDL by bending the knees more so with
this the shape is going to look kind of
like this and what this means is you're
going to bend the knees as much as
possible and reach back the cue for
these is picture me standing behind you
with a rope pulling the hips backwards
or better yet push the car door shut
with your butt if you do that you're
going to push push the hips back as far
as possible and you will naturally bend
the knees so any RDL is okay you can do
Romania deadlift with a barbell with
dumbbells you can do them off the pit
shark you can do any single leg version
of those my favorite single leg RDL
variations are the hip supported single
leg RDL and the single leg abducted RDL
but there are tons of good ones you
might just like braced single leg RDL or
even B stce rdl's another option here is
the Strat now we do this with the t-bell
standing on blocks you could use a
dumbbell or a cbell and the Strat lift
is amazing for glute think of it as a
squat where you don't quite go to
parallel or maybe just reach parallel
but you lean forward as far as possible
you're trying to stretch the glutes
maximally it's kind of like a mix
between a squat and a deadlift and
you're going to sink deep when you do
these you're going to feel these so much
in the glutes but you can also do these
single EG you can do kind of like I call
it a Bulgarian Romanian or a Romanian
Bulgarian where you kind of mix together
a Bulgarian split squat with a single
leg RDL but it looks like a hybrid now
unfortunately with with all of these
variations with any arol and good
morning even if you bend the knees
you're still going to work the
hamstrings a lot and same with the
stratal so again just do two sets you're
going to limit these CU you don't want
too much hamstring growth but they are
very effective glute Builders all right
what else is out the majority of lower
body isolation movement the only
isolated joint actions for lower body
that you are going to be doing a lot of
are the things the glute does isolated
hip extension isolated hip external
rotation and isolated hip abduction both
in the frontal and transverse plane but
you're not going to do any knee
extension no knee flexion no hip flexion
and no adduction ad deduction so this
means no leg extensions it would make no
sense to do leg extensions if you're
avoiding squats and leg presses and then
to do leg extensions again you are
trying to avoid growing the legs so no
leg extensions no reverse nordics no
[__] squats you're also going to do no
leg curl variations and this doesn't
just apply to the leg curl machine
seated leg curls lying leg curls
kneeling leg curls but all the leg curl
variations glute ham raises Nordic ham
curls gliding leg curls sliding leg
curls they're all out now hip flexion
most people don't do any hip flexion
exercises but you're not going to use
the multi- hiip for hip flexion and
you're not going to do any adduction
works so no seated hip adduction machine
and also no Copenhagen hip adduction so
what leg isolations are you going to do
you're going to do Kickbacks tons of
Kickbacks Kickbacks are your second best
friend if you're trying to grow the
glutes without growing the leg and you
can do all types of Kickbacks my
favorite Kickback machine is the glute
Builder we have one here at glute lab
back in the day I used to use the
reverse hyper we'd get underneath it and
we do pendulum Kickbacks and these are
very effective but you're most likely
going to do Kickbacks off the cable
column you can do them standing you can
do them swoopy hinge you can bend over
more you can do them high pulley or low
pulley you can do them kneeling now if
you do them kneeling or the high pulley
Kickback you are going to involve the
quads it's kind of like a step up it's
like a step down and this also applies
to using the assisted chin up and dip
machine where you do those step Downs so
limit those to two sets but the other
Kickback variations you can do three to
four sets they're all amazing we also
like to use ankle weights we use bands
all the time and do not underestimate
bands for glute growth banded Kickbacks
but especially band abductions which
I'll address in a minute you're also
going to do hyper variations now when I
say hypers I'm meaning back extensions
45 hypers and reverse hypers okay now
you can do these straight-legged but if
you do straight-legged it does work the
hamstrings so you're going to limit
those to two sets so all the different
types of horizontal back extensions
which you do off of ghd as well as 45°
hypers whereby there are a lot of
variations okay you can do them with
body weight you can use a dumbbell you
can use a band you can use a barbell you
can put your hands behind your back and
do single leg and now various equipment
manufacturers are making loaded hyper
devices now booty Builder makes the
cable back extension which is amazing we
love it here at glut lab and glute
Builder has a plate loaded version that
allows you to do straight leg and bent
leg and this is very popular as well you
can also do bent legged 45° hypers by
putting your feet against the wall while
using a standard 45° hyper but your gym
might not like that if you train in a
garage gym it's fine you can also do a
bent leg back extension variation with a
Smith machine off of a bench and like a
Smith machine or a barbell in the rack
like this it's a complicated setup it's
also a short range of motion there are
ways to increase the range of motion but
this is a way to do bent leg back
extension and the bent leg back
extensions are thought to reduce
hamstring involvement so when the legs
are bent you can do more of them because
it's not going to involve the hamstrings
it's going to involve more of the glutes
but what about reverse hypers okay
reverse hypers are great for glute
development you got to have the reverse
hyper unit though you can do body weight
variations all you want those are kind
of like accessories to throw in at the
end but if you do them with load you
need the reverse hyper station now you
can do them the standard way you can do
them double leg single leg you can also
do bent leg reverse hypers now people
might call this something different but
you do this off the Smith machine and
you're laying your torso on a bench and
you have bent legs and you're basically
kicking the barbell on the Smith machine
upwards it's complicated it takes some
getting used to but it is a very
effective glute Builder and the knees
stay bent so it's less hamstring more
glute so I covered hip extension
isolation movements what about abduction
now you can do standing hip abduction
straight to the side or you can go
diagonal rearward you should probably do
both because there's a lot of
subdivisions in the glute medius and
Minimus and you're doing frontal plain
hip abduction mainly to work the glute
medius and Minimus to build the upper
glutes of that shelf so you can use a
cable column you can do like I said
cable standing hip abductions or glut
medius Kickbacks which are 30° rearward
and that's thought to be more in the
plane of the glute medius now you can
also use an ankle weight or a glute loop
with these and we do tons of glute lab
abduction especially in GL glute lab San
Diego we use these with every session my
clients there love the glute Loop and we
learned that during the co quarantine
upper glutes were growing because people
were using their glut Loops every day
bands don't beat you up much the glute
medas can recover you could do the
standing band abduction pretty much on a
daily basis now you can also do extra
range sideline hip abduction if you're
really good you can throw an ankle
weight on these are brutal you can even
do those off the reverse hyper now you
can do glute media side bends on the
Smith machine you can do glute media
side steps up the cable column this is
kind of like a heavy length and partial
for the glut me you can also do bridge
abduction off the seated hip abduction
machine and this has become a staple
here at glute lab now we also have some
unique machines here we use the snow
angel machine all the time you probably
don't have this but this is awesome for
upper glutes now that covers frontal
plane hip abduction but what about
transverse plane hip abduction
transverse plane is when you're leaning
forward when you're bent over the main
exercise is the Leaning seated hip
abduction you know you're going to lean
as far as you can without rounding the
low back too much now we do these full
range of motion we do pulses you can do
single leg with this if you train from
home you can mimic this in two different
ways one with the sideline hip raise and
when you get good at those you can add
range of motion to it you can even add a
lot of range of motion to it which makes
it brutal you can also add load to those
if you want you can also do band leaning
seated hip abduction or even just seated
where you bring your knees to your chest
and do it from a seated position
obviously viously with the band you can
also do band hip hinge abduction and
then we have some unique machines here
for example the 3D abductors and when
you do transverse plane hip abduction
you're going to work the upper glute Max
more and the more you lean you might
involve the lower glute Max to a greater
degree now there's one abduction machine
that deserves special attention and this
is the Glu I just talked about the 3D
abductors the 3D abductors are hip
extension and hip abduction at the same
time but they're more Abduction the Glu
is more hip extension now we love the
Glu done just the standard way you can
use a wide stance a narrow stance you
can you can do them leaning back but you
can also lean forward and you can put
pads in between your knees so you can
get knees touching and knees to chest
knees touching knees to chest Glu Ator
is brutal it is one of the most
brilliant ideas ever known to glute
training I wish I invented the gluteator
machine because I told you earlier when
you're in deep deep hip flexion you're
necessarily going to use a lot of
adductor the adductor Magnus is heavily
activated in the bottom of a squat but
with the Glu you're going to be in that
deep Hip Flex position but you're going
to abduct at the same time and when you
abduct at the same time during hip
extension theoretically you're going to
greatly reduce the adductor involvement
and put more burden onto the gluteus
maximus so again knees touching and
knees to chest I wish all of you had a
gluteator machine because this is
amazing you're working the glutes very
hard in a stretch position like you
would in a squat without any of the
drawbacks it's safe no low back loading
you're not working your quads and you're
taking your adductors out of it
substantially as well it is brilliant
I've mentioned bands for hip abduction
for hip extension for Kickbacks but what
about wearing one during hip extension
exercises could that take out the
adductors a little bit theoretically it
could so if you don't want your
adductors to grow that's another
strategy that when you do squats when
you do leg press possibly for deadlifts
you'd have to have a strong band because
you don't flare the knees out during
deadlift but also during hip thrust and
glute Bridges you put the band around
your knees you're going to work a little
more upper glute Max and possibly take
the adductors out of it more research
needs to be carried out to see if that's
the case if it is that's huge now what
about Sumo lists what about Sumo style
variations can you do Sumo variations of
squats deadlifts Etc you can but again
only two sets yes Sumo might activate
the glutes more it doesn't stretch the
glutes as much but typically if you do
sumo squats you know Sumo deadlifts try
to keep the weight a little lighter and
focus on the Mind muscle connection
because people love these variations for
glutes but they are going to necessarily
work some quad hamstring and adductor so
limit your volume on those all right now
to the moment you've all been waiting
for what about hip thrust hip thrust are
my Mona Lisa I invented them in 2006
you're probably thinking I'm going to
say do all the hip thrust in the world
that's the secret to growing your glutes
without growing your legs and I think if
that's all you did was just hip thrust
like literally to the ladies watching
this and Bros too say you made it your
goal to hip thrust 300 15 lb for 20 reps
I'm not talking sloppy 3/4 reps I'm
talking all the way down all the way up
with a slight pause at the top and a
controlled Tempo on the way up and down
that's the best indicator for glute
growth that I know because it's very
hard to get there but hip thrusts
arguably lend themselves better to
Progressive overload than almost any
exercise out there they're very safe
they don't require a lot of coordination
they're super stable now at glute lab we
do barbell hip thrust we do rotisserie
hip thrust which we do off the Thruster
3.0 using the rotary pad that tilts now
interesting when you do rotisserie hip
thrust they're hardest at the bottom it
actually gets easier at the top and
that's not characteristic of the hip
thrust the rotisserie hip thrust changes
the hip extension torque angle curve and
makes it harder in the stretch so these
are awesome but when you do them
sometimes you're like man I miss doing
hip thrust with an emphasis on the
squeeze so for that reason we also
Target The Squeeze position during hip
thrust now normal hip thrust Target The
Squeeze position but we extra emphasize
it by doing pause reps 3 second pauses
we also do bar plus band and this is one
of my favorite ways to hip thrust I
actually do these off the Thruster Pro
we use the Thruster Pro here all the
time you can add bands to those to make
it extra hard at the lockout and finally
we also do pulses just the top range or
like one and a quars my point is we also
use the Smith machine for hip thrust we
do all types of hip thrust but again
don't do too much volume with these
because because they do grow the quads
and adductors a little bit and it's
probably better to rely on glute Bridges
now I want to mention two different
machines here because they kind of
belong in the category of hip thrust but
they do take your quads out of it so
this is a way to kind of do the hip
extension movement without feeling the
quads and that's the glute Builder
kneeling glute isolator this is one of
my favorite glute machines ever made now
I know your gym probably doesn't have
this if they do you're very lucky but I
do try to be thorough in my videos and
disc my methods here at glute lab this
machine is like a hip thrust it's bent
leg hip extension but it does not
involve the quads you feel almost all
glutes with this some people feel some
hamstring in an adductor but you can
also wear a band during these to kind of
prevent your knees from flaring out and
this could also theoretically limit some
adductor involvement now you can use a
band with these two which I like doing I
like using a band with the kneeling
glute isolator and really focusing on
the end range squeeze I also like the
Rogers reverse glute ham I liked it so
much that I bought the old school Hammer
straight model and made my own machine
which really worked the stretch position
so this yellow machine I'm showing you I
like the Rogers so much that I Ed the
Hammer Strength model to make it hardest
in the stretch position as you can see
with the Leever arm it's longest when
you get to the bottom of the movement we
only do length and partials with these
so this works the glutes in the stretch
position it takes the quads out of it
and I was thinking about manufacturing
this but I decided not to because a lot
of people hurt their low backs on it
it's like leg presses when you get in
deep hip flexions Some people post your
pelvic tilt and it's really brutal on
their low backs I happen to love it but
not everyone does but with the Rogers
it's not the hardest in the stretch
position so what we do is we load it up
extra heavy you need to partner with
these but we just do length and partials
off these we do the bottom half range of
motion for the stretch position we do
High Reps and it feels amazing for the
glutes so the Rogers for the stretch
kneeling glute isolator glute builder
for the squeeze these are awesome
exercises again you probably don't have
these These are specialty pieces but I
love them for growing the glutes without
growing the leg so the culture here is
amazing for hip thrust and I do think
you can do hip thrust the problem is
some people feel a lot of quads or a lot
of hamstrings when they hip thrust now
the Plotkin paper showed that the hip
thrust did not grow the hamstrings at
all but they did grow the quads half as
well as squats and they grew the
adductors a little bit less than half as
well as squats so they do grow the
adductors a little bit they they grow
the quads a little bit what would be an
even better strategy would be to perform
glute Bridges so glute Bridges
are your best friend I mentioned
Kickbacks are your second best friend
glute bridges are your best friend if
trying to grow your glutes without
growing the legs why because glute
Bridges take the quads out of it now
they don't move your hips through as
much range of motion you don't get as
much glute stretch so you're going to
have to do more volume you could also
wear a band around the knees because a
recent study showed that you did get
more upper glute Max activation not more
glute medius activation like You' think
so you don't wear a band for the glute
medius you wear a band for the glute Max
but it also slightly reduced hamstring
activity now it wasn't significant but
it was notable so let's talk about glute
Bridges you can do them on the floor
with a barbell it's really nice when you
have a spotter cuz you can use smaller
plates like 25lb plates they lift up one
of the sides you crawl under it they put
it on your lap and now the plates aren't
touching the floor you got tension
through the entire range of motion what
you don't want to do is use these big
plates with no bar pad or like a thin
bar pad and then now you have distance
to travel before your hips meet the bar
cuz then you're not getting tension
through a full range of motion but a
better solution is to use the Smith
machine the Smith machine is nice
because it's like a plate loaded device
you don't have to wrestle plates on the
ground at glute lab we have the Thruster
plates that I designed bigger sized
plates which makes the barbell like a
plate loaded device how nice is it to
load plates on the Smith machine or on a
plate loed machine or like a lake press
compared to on the bar when doing
deadlifts and hip thrust and you got to
wrestle those 45lb plates into the
position when you get super strong
that's a workout in and of itself so the
Smith machine is nice because you also
have tension throughout the full range
of motion when you go all the way down
there's still tension you can Elevate
the feet slightly for a little bit more
range of motion and if you do them from
the floor it's nice to have something
blocking you from moving rearward cuz if
you've done a lot of barbell glute
Bridges you tend to slide back when you
once you get very strong so when I
invented these in 2006 I would stand
above my clients and my my training bar
would stand above me I'd use the back of
their legs for stability now we put two
glute B benches against the wall or you
can use a bosu ball and put your neck on
it I personally like using the angled
Smith machine a little bit more when I
do angled Smith machine for hip thrust I
position myself to where the bar goes
away from me as I come up when I do
Smith machine glute Bridges and frog
pumps I position myself the opposite way
to where the bar goes this way as I come
up now some people believe that doing
hip thrust pulses just doing the top
portion of hip thrust would be better
for growing the glutes without growing
the legs you might have learned this as
a has glute bridge but we always did
them as just hypos pulses regardless of
the name you just do the top portion
those might be better at growing glutes
without growing the legs but I still
think glute Bridges would be ideal
compared to those because you're going
to reduce quad involvement cuz when
you're at the top of the hipos the quads
are going to contract now speaking of
frog pumps if you happen to feel frog
pumps a lot then they are an amazing
exercise for your glutes I love frog
pumps but I've walked with my feet out
my whole life my whole half my family
does my hips are extra rotated that's
due to my anatomy so frog pumps are
amazing for me I have one client that I
measured her glute activation with every
single exercise and frog pumps
outperformed everything by a landslide
she loves her frog pumps but other
people can't stand frog pump if you have
a particular hip anatomy where you like
to be narrow and some people even kind
of like their feet turned in a little
bit again everyone's hip Anatomy is
unique you got to match the exercise to
the individual and their hip Anatomy so
give frog pumps a try you might love
them like I do probably I used to say
two out of three but now I think it's
one out of two I think people are just
lying cuz they were so popular at one
point and then the pendulum went this
way frog pumps were on top of the world
and then they went this way and everyone
hated them what it should be right here
because for some people they're amazing
but give frog pumps a try I like them
off the Smith machine again angled Smith
machine going this way as I come up but
you could also do them with a dumbbell
in the lap if you do heavy dumbbell frog
pumps here's how you get them in
position you have the heavy dumbbell on
the side you roll to this side you pull
the dumbbell over and then onto your lap
we always have an ax balance pad or
something there for cushion so these are
an option too because these are going to
grow mostly glute without growing your
legs now I want to mention a special
category dual elevated hip thrust
there's two variations I want you doing
a lot of these you should do frequently
if you're trying to grow your glutes
without growing your legs the knee
banded dual elevated hip thrust and the
single leg dual elevated hip thrust so
you're going to use two benches you got
to set them up at the perfect distance
from another and they need to be stable
you're going to put your hands out
you're going to put your feet on the
corner and you're going to have a band
around your knees and you are going to
sink all the way down you sink super
deep now ideally your butt would just
touch the ground when you're in deep
maximal hip flexion and at that point
that's when I want you pushing the bands
out as hard as possible try to break the
band when you're at the bottom of the
movement because that's going to
increase glute activ ation in the
stretch and then come up all the way up
full range of motion don't focus on
Breaking the band at the top of the
movement let your knees come in a little
bit what I want you to do at the very
top is let your knees come in and push
tall make sure you reach a full glute
squeeze then sink down all the way if
you can do three sets of 20 of these
pushing out as hard as possible on the
way down with maximum stretch on the
bands in the Deep stretch at the bottom
of the movement with one minute rest
periods I guarantee you're going to like
this exercise you got to play around
with it once you learn it you're going
to love this movement that's going to
grow mostly glute it's not going to
involve a ton of quad hamstring or even
adductor so this should be a staple but
you don't progressively overload it you
progressively overload your glute
Bridges and maybe your hip thrusts but
exercise like these and kickbacks and
band work and ankle weight and cable
work those you don't always go for
Progressive overload those you do more
for the Mind muscle connection and the
Feld and then there's it single leg
counterpart you don't use a band with
these you just do them one leg at a time
but interestingly these are hardest at
the bottom of the movement it's really
tough at the bottom hard all the way
through now there's two more categories
of exercise that most people most glute
experts or like most trainers would look
at these two categories so and say it's
a waste of time it's a short Arc short
range of motion why even concern
yourself with hip external rotation or
posterior pelvic tilt but I do wonder if
you did enough volume with these two
exercise variations I think they could
grow the glutes they don't work much of
anything else and for hip external
rotation there's the cable cuff standing
hip external rotation these are
complicated it takes a while to get used
to but this does a great job of
isolating the glute Max doesn't work
your quads your hamstrings or your
adductors and you can also do band
standing hip external rotations you can
do this with a cable too we used to use
a band all the time I stopped
programming these because they're so
hard to teach everyone does them wrong
but if you do these right you feel
mostly all glute little bit of oblique
and then finally loaded postor pelvic
tilt while you can do this off the pit
shark off of a belt squat apparatus you
just load the plate pegs up super heavy
and you stand there and you do a
standing glute squeeze and when you do a
it's like squeezing your glutes against
resistance and this is all glute you're
not going to use anything else it's like
flexing your glutes against resistance
again it's a very short range of motion
it's probably just like 15° of posterior
pelvic tilt which you can think of as
hip hyperextension because with hip
hyper extension you you got the femur
moving across the stable pelvis with
postor pelvic tilt you got the pelvis
moving on a stable femur similar
Concepts now I don't expect to see
anyone doing this I just try to be
thorough because I really like these
there's another guy on Instagram who
loves these he's got huge glutes he does
them all the time these would
theoretically be great but you probably
don't want to do these at your gym I
just like to be thorough so these are
options as well all right so that wraps
up the exercise discussion now I'm just
going to summarize what I already taught
you if you are trying to grow your
glutes without growing your legs you're
going to do lots of glute Bridges if
you're a frog pump responder you can do
lots of frog pumps you're going to do
tons of Kickback all the Kickbacks
you're going to do lots of abduction
Abduction the frontal and transverse
plane if you like the hip external
rotation and postero pelvic tilt
exercise I taught you throw those in as
well you can do bent leg hyper
variations you can incorporate cables
you can use a lot of band work you can
do ankle weights none of these are going
to beat you up that much you can do
these very frequently with lots of
volume these exercises made up your
entire glute training protocol you would
grow mostly glutes without growing your
legs would you grow your glutes as
effectively as if you're doing all the
squats and lunges and rdls no you
probably wouldn't but you don't want the
leg growth that accompanies those so
those you can do with high volume and
frequency now let's discuss what you can
do with moderate volume and frequency
this would involve your hip thrust your
Sumo variations your glute dominant
squat lunge patterns remember the shape
your glute dominant staining hinge
patterns remember the shape and your
straight-legged hyper variation this
category will effectively grow your
glutes but it will also build some leg
muscle with it so you limit it and what
you're going to do no volume of are leg
extension variations leg curl variations
and hip flexion and hip adduction these
are out completely I'm very passionate
about this topic now I'm proud to say I
was the very first person to identify
this as a niche as a niche market even
within the glue training Community this
is a niche within a niche because there
are a lot of women who desire glute
growth without the leg growth and people
judge this people get so pissed but it's
fine it's okay it's perfectly okay to
want to grow your glutes without growing
your legs don't let people shame you for
it you know guys we want everything we
want traps we want all three delt heads
we want the pecs the lats the midback
the entire back we want the quads the
hammies the glutes the adductors give me
all the adductors and we want Cal growth
it is okay if you're a woman to kind of
like the way you look when you lean out
and get slender but you just want a
little more glute shade you just want a
rounder perk your butt Meat Heads and
advanced lifters get pissed at this goal
but they don't have your genetics and
they don't have your goals so don't feel
bad if it's your desire to train this
way I think I wrote my first blog post
in 2013 about this and I even called it
growing your glutes without growing the
legs and it's funny over the years that
sentence got used over and over by
everyone I'm proud to say that I was I
think I'm the first person to write
about that I also made a YouTube video
in 2021 I think it has around a million
views but this one's better why because
methods evolv science evolved we come up
with new variations more studies are
published we gradually become more
effective over time I did create a
program and I sold it as an ebook
growing your glutes without growing the
legs people loved it there's two quick
things I want to discuss before I sign
off and the first thing is that I don't
like talking about this because I don't
like fearmongering most of my clients do
squats they do deadlifts they do all the
list all the exercis we talked about in
this video they do all of them and they
look amazing a lot of women think
they're quad dominant they think they're
legs are too big but really they're just
not happy with their body fat and think
about this when men get overweight do we
go oh I'm abominant I got all this fat
here I'm abominant I don't want to do
any ab exercises typically we'll say we
want to do ab exercises cuz we think
it's going to melt fat in that area but
that's not the way it works spot
reduction is a myth but some women will
carry a lot of fat in their legs and
they think oh I don't want to build leg
muscle but once you get lean once you
get down to like you know 18% body fat
16% you'll probably like the way your
legs look even if they do have some
muscle on them now not everyone is like
that there are some people I've trained
who get too big of quads for their
liking or too big of hamstrings or
adductors but in general you should try
to get down to a reasonable body fat
level and get strong everywhere before
you decide that you want to grow your
glutes without growing your legs because
building muscle all over for example
with my strong lifting program that gets
you lean that makes you recm if you stay
the same weight if you lose weight
that's going to help you keep your
muscle and lose just fat for weight loss
but a lot of times people think they
shouldn't do any squats or any stiff leg
deadlifts or any lunges when they
actually would benefit from doing them
they'd look just fine if they pair that
with the caloric deficit and reduce
their body fat and the last thing I want
to mention is in general don't listen to
a lot of the Bros on social media they
will give you the worst advice if your
goal is to grow your gluts without
growing your legs because they'll tell
you just squat don't do Kickbacks don't
do these stupid exercise don't use bands
just Squat and they say this because
they want quads they like adductors I
like quads and adductors if I told you
to train the way I train you'd be
hammering your quads and hamstrings all
the time but I do realize that that's
not many women's goals most of you are
fine doing a little bit of squats little
bit of Romanians little bit of lunges
but you do want to do a lot of glute
work and you want to train glutes three
times a week and you want to do hip
thrust every session you want to throw
in Kickbacks and abduction every session
that is the way that most bikini
competitors train that is the way the
ladies with the greatest glute
development in the world train listen to
them not the Bros they tend to give the
worst advice because they've never
trained glutes in their entire life they
train legs and their glutes happen to
grow from it but most of them have never
even done a hip thrust or a kickback or
used bands for abduction or anything
like that and therefore they don't have
expertise on the matter and shouldn't be
listened to they might understand
hypertrophy in general but they don't
understand trying to grow the glutes
without growing the legs and even if you
don't have this goal this video is still
useful because variety is the spice of
life we need lots of variation in
strength and conditioning because
sometimes you get injured think of
yourself as a carpenter a good Carpenter
is going to have a large toolbox right
you're going to have all these specialty
tools yes you're going to use your
hammer and your screwdriver a lot more
often than the other tools but
throughout the year you end up using all
of them you know how how to use all of
them the right time and the right place
that's how strength and conditioning
work I hope you found this video to be
useful please give it a like if you like
what you saw please leave me a comment
let me know what you're thinking I'm
trying to get to a million followers in
2025 I'm committed to coming out with a
video at least once a week preferably
once every 5 days I got Alex back as you
can see we're doing our best if you're
new here welcome to the channel I'm
Brett kerus aka the glute guy please
subscribe to my channel if you like
hearing about the glutes or all things
Sports Science because I'm going to make
a lot of videos on the science strength
and hypertrophy training